[Music]
Stanford
University all right let's um let's
start let's try to get to the heart of
some of the aspects of string theory
which uh are really very Central we
haven't talked about them but we've set
up many of the questions we've set up
many of the
ideas
um I want to show you
first something which has both to do
with why string theory has gravity in it
and it has to do with why there are such
unusual
constraints on the allowable kinds of
string theories that you can have I'm
not going to actually get into 26 or 10
Dimensions but I'm going to give you an
example which shows just uh how tightly
constrained
the idea of string theory is compared to
the idea of Point
particles
um Point particles can move in curved
spaces a very very simple
example would just
be this is something you can uh you
can look up I suspect in elementary
mechanics textbooks or AR particles
moving on a curved
surface curved surface could be a sphere
doesn't matter some sort of curved
surface it could be positively curved
negatively
curved in fact it doesn't have to be
two-dimensional but I'm drawing it as
two-dimensional let's say a
two-dimensional surface and a particle
on it a
particle is described by a point on that
space a point and a velocity if you want
to know uh the future history of it and
moves on a
trajectory moves on a trajectory and it
satisfies an equation of motion the
equation of motion is some form of
Newton's
equations uh projected onto the
surface what how does a point particle
move I'm thinking now about um ordinary
non-relativistic particles moving on a
curved uh surface without any forces the
forces of course are there to hold it in
the surface but other than the forces
needed to hold it in the surface no
other forces how does the point partical
move anybody
know moves on a geodesic which is
another way of saying it moves as
straight as possible uh doesn't deviate
to the left doesn't deviate to the right
it moves along a geodesic that's right
if there are forces on it of one kind or
another uh then it may move in a more
complicated trajectory
you could
imagine that this wouldn't be consistent
you could imagine that it might not be
consistent how could it fail to be
consistent uh to write down it's just a
differential equation just a Newton type
differential equation here's a way that
it could be Inc which it of course is
not inconsistent it's perfectly
consistent uh as long as the surface is
smooth as long as the surface is smooth
differentiable all the good things at
nice surface have but what do you really
mean by a uh the motion of a particle
satisfying a differential equation as
always you mean break up the trajectory
into a lot of little pieces replace
derivatives by
distances and uh think of um a discrete
version of it that's the first step
derivatives are really
differences uh and then take the limit
take the limit
in the appropriate way of more and more
little time
intervals question how do I know that
the limit exists how do I know that the
limit exists could it be that as I put
more and more points in there that the
limit of whatever it is you're
calculating the trajectory itself how do
I know that the limit exists well uh
these are just described by ordinary
differential equations people have been
studying differential
equations uh since the mathematician
differential was a young man and uh we
know that the solutions of these things
are smooth regular and have good
limits okay now you could ask a more
complicated question you could say wait
a minute I'm really interested in
quantum
mechanics and in quantum mechanics we
have a more complicated kind of question
instead of just looking for at
trajectory we ask questions for example
what's the amplitude that if a particle
starts here that at a later time we will
Discover it here we find again there is
an action principle but the action
principle is not to find the trajectory
of least action which gives a
differential equation but to use a path
integral and a path integral sums over
all trajectories including wildly
varying
ones again a trajectory being defined in
terms of breaking it up into little
pieces and then taking a limit now how
do I know that the limit exists yeah are
those trajectories all inside the
surface yeah they're all inside the
surface yeah everything takes place
inside the surface yes good point yeah
we're talking about physics in in a
surface on a Surface whatever you want
to call it those features which are
completely independent of how the
surface um
uh that depend on the geometry of the
surface but not anything outside the
surface yeah all right so how do I know
that this very very complicated path
integral structure exists in the sense
that it has a limit a limit as you take
the grain structure finer and finer
there the answer is much much more
complicated
but it's equivalent to solving the AR
Schrodinger equation on on the surface
and again that's a more complicated kind
of equation it's a partial differential
equation and partial differential
equations are more
difficult but partial was a very smart
guy and he figured out how partial
differential equations work and we know
from 19th century physics and so forth
that the limits do exist they do make
sense string theory is more subtle
infinitely more
subtle in string theory we're not
talking about a point particle we're
talking about an extended object now
that's the string itself imagine a
string which is constrained to
move in a surface and this surface does
not have to be two-dimensional but as I
said I'm going to think about two
dimensions
here's the
string and it's a quantum mechanical
string which means it's subject to uh to
vibrations in fact uh just to just to
pick an
example let's talk about String
Theory where the space that the string
moves on other words real space the
space that the string moves on is a
sphere and it happens to be a sphere
with radius on
R it's a sphere with radius
R oh let's do a point particle first in
fact let's do a classical Point particle
first point particle moves on a
sphere what is its kinetic energy or its
lran as always it's just 1 12 mv^
2 mass time velocity squared which is
also the momentum squared divided by
twice the mass let's write it that way
p^2 ided by twice the mass but now
there's a constraint and the constraint
is that the particle has to stay on the
sphere
nevertheless this velocity what that
means is this velocity Vector is in the
surface of the sphere the momentum
Vector is also in the surface of the
sphere but other than that it's just a
standard classical mechanics now if we
were doing quantum
mechanics then on a sphere
sphere is the motion of a particle on a
sphere moves in a circle of course a
great circle great circle of size R the
momentum is
quantized how do you see that the
momentum is quantized well there's
various ways to see it but uh let me
just give you a very simple way if the
momentum is p and the radius of the
sphere is R what is the angular
momentum P
PR PR so the angular momentum
l is equal to P *
R in magnitude anyway and angular
momentum we know is quantized we know
that it's quantized in units of
um
uh H bar so some quantized angular
momentum here I'm not even going to
bother writing it angular momentum is
fundamental because it's quantized so it
pays to rewrite the energy in terms of
the angular momentum let's write p
as L / R and stick it into here then it
becomes
l^2 ided twice M let's see what is it
twice M and now r s
right Mr s you know what Mr squ is
called moment of
inertia the moment of inertia in this
case of the point particle over here and
the symbol for it
I l^2 over twice the moment of
inertia so what characterizes the motion
of this
particle is first of all its angular
momentum but the moment of inertia the
moment of inertia plays a central role
in the uh energy levels in all of the
properties of the trajectories but in
particular the energy levels when we're
doing quantum mechanics
and that's an important formula good
right so uh classical mechanics of Point
particles is described this way and the
quantum mechanics of Point particles is
also described this way L being angular
momentum we know how to deal with
angular momentum it's
quantized okay so all of that is
straightforward now we want to talk
about a string a string moving on this
sphere here it is it's constrained to be
in the sphere the sphere the the
spherical surface is all there is there
is no outside the spherical surface and
inside there only the spherical surface
itself however as I said the spherical
surface could be higher dimensional but
for the moment just two dimensional and
it's going to move
around
good how do I know that in the limit
that I think of the string as a
collection of little
points how do I know that the properties
of this little string have good
limits the answer is they don't F we we
the not that we don't know the answer is
that the limits don't exist right so let
me show you why and what happens the
first thing is to understand a little
more about the size and shapes of
strings we want to understand a little
more about
them so let's calculate how big
statistically the string has Zer point
oscillations the oscillators in the
string are constantly vibrating even in
the ground state because they're
vibrating they give the string a little
size they give the string a little size
and I'm interested in trying to figure
out how how big that string is when the
zero point oscillations are included so
how do I do that I go back to a formula
that we had on the Blackboard maybe the
first or second
lecture let's do open strings just for
Simplicity remember this formula the
position of a point on the string what
is Sigma Sigma is the parameter along
the string
is equal to a sum over
oscillators each
oscillator has a frequency associated
with it so an n and we have let's call
it a +
n plus a minus
n
cine of n Sigma and there's one other
thing a square root of n downstairs does
everybody remember that probably not but
if you go back in your
notes H yes yeah there may be factors of
two I I don't remember in
detail uh whether the factor of two sits
in front of it or not but that's not
important this is the structure of
it now what do I want to calculate I
want to calculate in the ground state of
the string ground state of the string is
a state with no oscillation
I want to calculate the mean size of it
the average size of it so the average
size of it let's calculate the average
squared size this Square X but Square x
x squ at any point Sigma an arbitrary
Point
Sigma what does that give us that gives
us
sum on n and a sum on M we're going to
have a + n Plus a -
n time a + m + a -
M over Square < TK of n Square < TK of M
cosine n Sigma cosine M
Sigma I've just written down this
expression twice once as a sum over n
and once as a sum over M I've done
nothing special now what I want to
calculate is its average value in the
ground state average value in the ground
state in quantum mechanics we represent
like this o stands for the ground state
string and we want to calculate its
average
value right that means we want to
calculate the average of this in the
simultaneous ground state of all of the
oscillations now you might think the
answer is zero
right well that's not quite true every
oscillator in its ground state quantum
mechanical oscillator has a little bit
of Zero Point Energy that little bit of
Zero Point Energy gives it an average
fluctuation in
position or in this case in uh
in X itself and how do we calculate it
let's look at the various terms here
we're going to calculate the ground
state expectation value of this o o
the important pieces are these creation
and Annihilation
operators what happens if I take the
piece with A+ time A+ can that have an
expectation value for in the in the
ground state well no it can't and the
reason is two A+ when they act to the
right create a state with two extra
units of
energy you've raised the oscillator in
twice and that has no overlap with the
ground state at
all okay so the term with two a
pluses that uh that can't contribute to
this how about the term with 2 a
minuses what does a minus do when it
hits the ground
state it kills it right it's also true
incidentally when A+ acts to the left it
kills this so the terms with A+ A+ and a
minus a minus give
nothing what
about A+ * a minus this A+ * a minus
okay well you just said that kills the
left kills the right right so that's not
there but what about the term a minus
A+ sounds good sounds good let's so look
let's look at
it a minus * A+ that's still there if
it's zero so be it but I don't see any
reason why it should be
zero okay what does it say it says we
create one unit of excitation for the M
oscillator this says we remove one unit
of excitation for the nth
oscillator can you remove a unit other
than the one you put in no no so this
can only be nonzero if n is the same as
m but if n is the same as M what do you
get Delta fun chronical Delta one these
are all discreet so they're not
continuous
variables uh you get one if n equals
m and zero otherwise in other words the
sum of N and M is only a single
sum it's the sum of
N of
a minus N A + n over Square < TK of
n sorry not n n sare root of n * root of
n that's just
n and then
cosine
squared of n
Sigma now cosine squar is always
positive and it averages to about a
half cosine of n Sigma is a function
which looks like
this if you square it of course it's
above the axis because the square is
always positive and it averages to about
a
half that's good enough for our purposes
it's it's never negative you can't get
any cancellation and it kind of
oscillates around the half so for most
purposes it's sufficient just to call
this a half
that's about
right o
o and what is this thing this thing is
just
one you create a particle or you create
an excitation of the nth oscillator and
then you take it out that average value
is just one so we now have an answer the
answer is that the that X squar now I'll
tell you what x squ means in a moment
it's
equal the 1/2 is not the important thing
here just sum on
n 1/
n now first of all what is X squ what is
what is X I wrote here x of Sigma but I
left out one term do anybody know what
the term that I left out
is the center of mass
motion there's one term which
corresponds to zero frequency which is
just the center of
mass so really the thing that I've
calculated was the average
of the position of the string at Point
Sigma minus the position of the center
of mass think about that for a moment
what's it
mean you have a string in this case an
open
string and a center of mass is may or
may not be on the string
but different points on the string are
separated from the center of
mass the average the average separation
from the center of mass is a measure of
the size of the
thing the center of mass is where the
center of mass is and if the points of
the string are not anticenter of mass
that means that it's been spread
out if this is non zero it means string
is is extended in size and here we're
calculating it and we find out that x^2
is this sum of 1 /
n
trouble trouble big trouble why why is
it trouble it's infinite it's
infinite now most of these oscillations
are incredibly
rapid the large n oscillations are very
very rapid
oscillations maybe we should just
say really all those very very rapid
oscillations are
unphysical cut them off only take the
first in the first 25 oscillations into
account and see what happens well then
we'll only have log of 25 and log of 25
is not a very big number how big is log
of 25 log to the base e of 25 not very
big
uh that's a small number a moderate
number but um then we're not doing
String Theory we're essentially doing a
string of 25
particles we're not doing String Theory
uh we've got to go to the Limit n equals
z now it's an extremely remarkable
thing that this causes no problem s for
the scattering of strings in flat space
in flat space it's a it's it's a real
magical uh very very delicate
cancellations that make sure that this
string which is essentially infinitely
big with rapid fluctuations taking place
all over the place doesn't bombard other
strings far away even though it's
extended out all over the place they're
very rapid fluctuations it's an amazing
set of cancellations which makes sure
that all of this works out but that
those cancellations don't always work
they work in some geometries and not in
others so I'm going to show you what
goes wrong on the sphere and it doesn't
go wrong in flat space first of all the
message of all of this
is First Step terminate the sum at some
Maximum
n in ma a maximum frequency later on
we're going to have to repair the damage
by letting the maximum frequency get
larger now we can ask how does this
string
behave as a function of n
Max in flat space well here's the way to
think about it as a function of n
Max the string occupies a certain region
of
space it's the region of space whose x
squared or R whose R
2 is
equal to the logarithm of n
Max the higher we make n Max the bigger
it seems to spread out but very very
slowly but nevertheless it seems to
spread out well if this is moving in
flat space it has a energy which is just
1 12 it's mass time time p^ 2 it doesn't
matter that it's spread out the motion
of a center of mass of a billiard ball
this big that big moves exactly the same
way as the motion of the center of mass
of a proton it moves uh the center of
mass well of course it's not the same
way it has a different Mass but in flat
space the motion of a particle the
center of mass of a particle separates
off the fact that it's an extended
object you don't have to remember the
fact that it's uh that it's uh extended
if you're just interested in the center
of mass motion but that's not true in
curved space in curved space they don't
separate off so easily so let's see if
we can figure out what's happening
here here's the string let's put the
string up at the North Pole here the
string is up at the North
Pole and if I make as my first
approximation that there's only one or
two
oscillating modes well we could start
with no oscillating modes if there were
no oscillating modes then the string
would be a point it wouldn't be spread
out at
all it would be a like a just be a point
then the string would just be a point
and it would be over here and it would
move as an ordinary Point particle how
does a point particle move it moves with
an energy which is the square of the
angular momentum over the
moment of inertia and what's the moment
of inertia it's just proportional to
mass times the radius squared time the
radius squar of the sphere if we set M
to one then it would just be the square
of the radius of the sphere so this
point here would move around the
sphere on great
circles and it would move with an energy
which would be controlled by
the radius of the sphere the radius of
the sphere we go into this calculation
in terms of the moment of
inertia okay now let's take into account
that as we add more modes of
oscillation the string starts to spread
out it starts to get a size and grows
not grows with time but grows with more
and more um oscillations here starts to
get bigger
it fills up some region which looks
about like that incidentally if you ask
what does it look like on the average it
simply looks like a
tangle the more modes that you add the
more and the bigger the tangle
is right it's fluctuations on top of
fluctuations on top of
fluctuations and this thing starts to
get bigger
now think about its motion around the
center of mass of it think of the center
of mass of it moving on the same great
circle the center of mass will still
move on the great circle but what about
its moment of
inertia moment of inertia about an
axis here's an axis it's moving it's
going around that axis the relevant
quantity is the moment of inertia about
that axis and it's governed
by the square of the distance to the
axis the moment of inertia about an
axis is proportional to a
sum it's an integral over the mass
distribution each little piece of the
mass
distribution you take the mass of that
little piece and you multiply it by the
square of the distance to the uh uh to
the axis that you're rotating about now
notice that this point over here is
closer to the axis than this point up
here in fact let's go to extremes let's
suppose we include so many modes that
uh let's let me draw this
better droops down to about over here
it's rotating around the sphere this way
it's on the sphere it's not inside the
sphere it's on the sphere the point on
the sphere up here that is a distance R
from the uh from the
uh uh from the axis what about this
point over here how far from the axis is
it is it less than or more than
R looks less than doesn't it but that's
deceptive because we forgot that the
sphere is really a sphere
it's really a sphere I've it's like
moving the point down to
here okay with the axis going in this
direction it would be the same distance
so this this point over here which is
out here somewhere is the same distance
from the axis as this
point okay but how about this point over
here it really is closer to the axis
than the point up
here so what's going to happen when I
calculate the
um
uh when I calculate
the moment of
inertia the moment is it going to be
bigger or smaller or exactly the same as
it was when I pretended all of the
string was at a single
point it's going to be
smaller right it's going to be
smaller the uh the mass of the string is
the same incidentally that does not
change when you add add more uh more
modes just oscillates differently but
the mass the amount of mass that's there
is just the sum of the masses of little
Point particles that make it up the mass
stays the same but the moment of inertia
gets
smaller the meaning of that is that the
quantum mechanics
behaves you can either say you can say
it two ways you could say the string is
spread out and like that and therefore
closer to the axis
or you can just say it's as if the
string moved on a smaller
sphere it's as if all of the quantum
mechanics essentially
takes behaves as if the
string was a
point but was a point on a smaller
sphere
okay but the more modes that you
add the bigger the string
gets eventually if you add enough modes
it's going to grow so that it's almost
as big as the entire
sphere in other words well let's let's
go to some extreme where it where it
fills up a good fraction of the sphere
in that case the effective moment of
inertia is going to be much smaller than
uh than the moment of
inertia with would have been if it would
have been a point particle but even
worse there's no limit or at least as n
gets larger and larger the string begins
to cover the whole sphere and the
effective moment of inertia is actually
zero the average position of it is right
at the
center if the effective moment of
inertia is zero well that's a zero in
the denominator here that's not a good
thing uh for uh for the motion of
anything
why why is it zero I mean it's still
spread around there it's as if the thing
well it's it no it's not zero it's not
zero but okay um yeah yeah no no you
have to be it it does go to zero but you
have to be you have to think about it in
a different way what you do is you
say the string behaves if you if you
only take into account let's say a dozen
normal modes then the string
behaves as if it were a point on an in
on a closer Circle but now instead of a
dozen normal modes let's take two dozen
normal
modes then what it does is it starts to
behave like a
string on this inner surface
here this is not obvious this is what is
called renormalization group
renormalization group is a way of f
following the system as you add more and
more degrees of freedom what you can
follow it honestly is for a small change
in
nmax but once you follow for a small
change in inmax and you find out that
it's behaving as if it were a lump let's
say this
big now you add more structure it begins
to behave like a like a a collection of
lumps that also form a string
and you just do the whole process over
again you say with a dozen normal modes
it behaves as if it were a more or less
a point on an inner region here now you
add more of them and it begins to make
itself into a string of these same
lumps that has the effect of pushing it
in again and uh eventually it just
pushes it to
zero so there is no limit there is no
limit the limit of a string moving on a
curved surface and this is due to the
curvature if it weren't due to the
curvature you wouldn't have this effect
it's due to the curvature of the
sphere this happens in any number of
Dimensions uh that as you add more and
more
modes
the behavior does not tend to a finite
limit
it just tends to behave
eventually as the motion of a string on
an extremely small infinitesimal sphere
which means in the denominator here a
zero and that's not a good
theory that's what
happens so the answer is strings on
spheres are not good strings on spheres
don't make
sense what is the condition for a
surface and a surface I'm not I'm using
the
term in a general sense it could be it
doesn't have to be two dimensional it
could be 3 4 10 26 Dimensions whatever
whatever the number of dimensions of
space what we mean by a surface is a
geometry with a metric a geometry with a
metric a ranian
geometry oh what are the
roles what you really want
is a set of rules which approach a limit
if you're near that limit then in other
words by a limit I mean the limit that
as nmax gets bigger and bigger you don't
want the answers to change as nmax goes
from 100 billion to 100 billion plus one
or for that matter for 100 billion to to
200 billion you want the answer to
stabilize that's called a fixed point
you want the answer to stabilize and not
to change so what you would like is a
situation with a
geometry that when you do exactly the
same thing the geometry does not seem to
change in other words we could Define an
effective geometry for a string we take
the geometry and now we sort of average
over the properties of an extended
object and that defines the motion on a
different
surface different surface being the
effect Ive surface that the spread out
string moves
on as long as it keeps changing on us as
we increase n Max there will not be a
limit a limit would mean that at some
point as you add more and more structure
to the string the effect of geometry
stops changing and tends to some limit
that limit will be a good
geometry for for string theory to make
sense
on okay so I'll tell you what one can do
this calculation very precisely for an
arbitrary
geometry and you can
ask when you
add additional modes let's say you add
you go up to some
nmax and you add one more mode how does
the effective geometry that the string
moves on how does it
change what how do you describe a ranian
geometry what's the what's the variables
that you describe a remani in
Geometry the metric
right the metric tensor that's the
description of the geometry G mu new of
X this don't think of it now as the
gravitational field although it is the
gravitational field it's the metric of
space g mu new of
X we have a
geometry could be the sphere could be
anything else could be a hyperboloid it
could be a thing with Wiggles in it it
might be space-time geometry
itself
okay a string moving on such a
geometry the effect of geometry will
change a little
bit why because the string is is spread
out a little bit the center of it will
move in a way that responds to a
slightly different geometry and so we
can ask what's the change in the effect
of geometry when you add
one more
mode okay the answer is first of all
that it depends on the curvature if the
sphere weren't curved this would not
have happened this has to do with the
fact that the sphere was
curved so whatever the change in the
geometry is if it were flat it would not
change but if it's curved it does change
in general so there must be on the right
hand side
something which involves the curvature
tensor okay the left hand side is a
tensor with a mu and a new a second rank
tensor
symmetric just a so the right hand side
has to be a
tensor it's not gunu itself it's some
other tensor that has to do with the
curvature if it weren't curved nothing
would happen so it must be that on the
right hand side is something involving
curvature curvature is called capital r
and the full curvature tensor has four
indices it's a thing with four
indices are let's say mu
new no let's not call it mu and new for
the moment let's just call it Alpha Beta
Gamma
Delta you can put all four downstairs
upstairs doesn't matter it's of
uh written with one index upstairs and
uh some indices
downstairs okay this equation doesn't
make sense the indices don't match but
is there a thing that you can make out
of the curvature tensor which also has
only two indices in which is symmetric
anybody know the reachy tensor the richy
tensor is
simply the contraction alpha alpha mu
new
that's called R
muu and it's the Richi
tensor so when a careful calculation let
me see is it plus or minus I think it's
minus
minus minus the REI
tensor it corresponds to the sphere
getting smaller when you add more
structure that's why that's where
there's a minus there this is the equ
equ that governs how the effective
geometry of the string changes as you
add more and
more
uh fluctuation to the
stren mathematicians have a name for
this
equation it's called Richi
flow Richi flow is a tremendously
important part of mathematics and it's
an equation that if you start with a G
ometry and then you change it in accord
with this
equation what happens is it starts to
deform and it flows the geometry
flows okay it's called Richi flow it has
very important applications in
mathematics I don't know whether it was
discovered by string theorists or first
discovered by mathematicians I'm not
sure
but that's what this is It's a fuzzing
out of the geometry because the point
have gotten fuzzed out it's a kind of
diffusion of the geometry which is
fuzzing it out the points have gotten
fuzzed out by the fluctuations of the
strings and the effect of geometry
behaves this way is there is there a
function of in Max there somehow is that
no this is the change when you all right
the change when you add the it's the
logarithmic change it's the change when
you change the cut off by uh by a factor
yeah yeah uh
yeah Chang in the logarithm of the cut
off to be
exact but it doesn't matter it's the
change as you change the cut off now
what we're looking for though is
geometries which don't change when you
change the cut off we want something
stable we want to say we're talking
about string theory on this or that
space we don't want the description of
it to keep wandering away as we add more
of these modes so what we really want
are
geometries which are stable and don't
change when we change the when we change
things when we change the cut off what
does that mean that means
geometries where the reachy tensor is
zero if the reachy tensor is
zero that's like saying it's well it's
not like saying it's flat flat space is
does have Rey tens of zero of course it
has all of its components of curvature
equal to zero so flat space is an
example of
this question is are there other
examples of spaces this is called reachy
Flat if a space has Vanishing Richi
tensor it's called Richi flat Richi
flatness is essentially the condition
that strings can propagate
sensibly uh on that
geometry okay good limits as the number
of modes goes to Infinity all right so
there's there's a condition on the
geometry um it's called Richi
flatness it could be the SpaceTime
geometry that the string is moving in in
fact uh that's the way you'll think
about it for the moment the space-time
geometry has space directions time
directions but uh anybody know what that
equation that equation has another
meaning
yeah it's essentially the Einstein field
equation for the gravitational field
Einstein field equation for the geometry
it's the vacuum Einstein field
equations
Einstein in vacuum no matter just
gravity and
curvature I'll write out the Einstein
equations for you and then I'll show you
that it's the same as uh
as this equation anybody remember the
Einstein field
equations something equals rals
T something like that something like
that it's it's a tensor called capital G
mu new it's called the Einstein tensor
and the reason it's called capital G is
it's got something to do with gravity
but it's also equal the r mu
new minus 12 G mu new
R okay where R what is r r is R alpha
alpha or yeah R alpha alpha and that's
equal to T muu where T muu is the energy
momentum
tensor energy momentum tensor means the
energy momentum of cookies the energy
momentum of the cup of coffee but not
the energy momentum of the gravitational
field everything is in here
other than
gravity okay the vacuum Einstein field
equations mean the field equations for
the gravitational field when there's
nothing on the right hand side
zero that's called Einstein vacuum
equations are there any interesting
solutions to this equation what are the
what are the solutions of this schild is
one but schild has a nasty singularity
in it so it's uh it's it's
uh no um well Robinson Walker also has
singularities but
uh
h no the c space requires a cosmological
const just gravitational
waves just gravitational waves just
that's it gravitational waves it's
similar to Maxwell's equations without
sources Maxwell's equations without
charges do they have any solutions yeah
just a plain or just electromagnetic
radiation uh gravitational radiation
also exists the solutions of this kind
of equation here in four-dimensional
SpaceTime in four-dimensional SpaceTime
other words one time Direction three
space directions the solutions of this
include all kinds of things like
gravitational waves interacting
gravitational waves gravitational waves
can do complicated
things uh in Einstein gravity but
there's a whole family an infinite
parameter family of complicated
Solutions of these
equations all right now we're interested
in Richi flat this doesn't say R mu new
equals zero but let's take let's
take when I put one index upstairs and
one index downstairs that's called the
trace when I when I sum over Alpha and
Alpha all right
let's um let's raise one index let's
write it
R mu
newus
12 G mu new R alpha alpha equal
Z what's G what is this thing
here one mu or G with one M downstairs
and one upstairs that's a chronical
Delta right right so that's just
the uh chronica
Delta Delta
muu Delta Mu new and now set mu equal to
new and
sum call them both Alpha R alpha
alpha
equals 12 or minus sorry is equal to 12
what happens to this when you set mu and
new both equal to Alpha and
sum I think you get four right four for
the four directions of space so this
becomes either plus or minus a half
maybe times 2 R alpha
alpha it does it does not say let's see
um to it's two alog
together it's either plus two or minus
two I can't remember but but it's quite
inconsistent unless R is zero right this
equation
implies that this is called the Richi
Scala or the curvature Scala the
curvature Scala must vanish if
Einstein's field equations are correct
if they're satisfied so this is not
there and the Einstein field equations
in empty space is just r muu equal 0
what have we learned
we've learned that the only acceptable
geometries in which strings make stable
sense and in which the geometry doesn't
change and change and change and change
as you add more degrees of freedom are
the solutions of Einstein's field
equations you can quantize strings in
background geometries which satisfy
Einstein's equations and you cannot
formulate them correctly in spaces which
don't satisfy Einstein's equations
that's pretty impressive that out of the
consistency
condition for strings to have a well-
defined geometry in the limit that the
number of degrees of freedom becomes
infinite you derive Einstein's field
equations for uh for
geometry that's an extremely impressive
fact question yes yeah would there be a
connection between the uh tens Z and the
idea that that that it Ms
[Applause]
informally it it's very closely
connected to conformal invariance but
not conformal invariance in SpaceTime
conformal invariance of the world
sheet is very closely connected with
that it is actually the condition for
the conformal invariance
but they they are Ed
yes
uh but I've showed you the simplest way
to think about
it
that in general because the string
spreads out the effective geometry that
it sees is different than the geometry
you started
with and in general doesn't approach a
limit if it does approach a limit it's
because at the
limit the reachi tensor is zero so
reachy tensor being zero are special
okay now we want to come to a
subject oh incidentally I've um cheated
a little I hav't cheated I haven't told
you the whole story the whole story is
that it really doesn't work except if
you're in the right number of
Dimensions uh the subtleties of this
kind of thing are quite subtle and it
really only works that the answers
become independent of of n max if if the
geometry is richy flat and in the right
number of
Dimensions 10 for super String Theory 26
for
uh so that's the basic principle the
answers should have finite limits as n
Max goes to
infinity and that is enough to tell you
that the geometries that you move in
must be Solutions of Einstein field
equation they must be Gra gravitational
waves and other
things now we want to
come to the problem of what do we do
with 10 or 26 Dimensions how do we make
sense out of
them and the answer is called
compactification compactification is
simply the process of taking however
many dimensions we want to get rid of by
getting rid of them we don't really get
rid of them
but we make them small enough that they
become invisible except to very very
small things we want to roll them up
into
little
manifolds
that are Co grained uh apparatuses don't
see they may affect and they will affect
they'll have you know real serious
effect on the structure of particles and
so forth the structure of Elementary
particles type of Elementary particles
that you can have but they won't be
visible as directions that uh that you
can move around
in all right so let's talk about
compactification we have let's take the
case of super String Theory where there
are 10 dimensions of space time which is
six too
many one good
thing is that the 10 dimensions of
SpaceTime have only one time and six
space and uh nine space dimensions we
would have we would not know what to do
with two time Dimensions what um physics
with some extra space dimensions that's
that's no problem things just get to
move and more but what would mean to
have more than one time beats me and uh
probably doesn't mean
anything so super string theory is a
theory with nine spatial dimensions and
one time di it kind of ties into what
Jeff's question earlier was about
degrees of freedom versus dimension of
space in essence what I was trying to
say never mind whether you know there's
12 or only six the idea is that the more
moving Parts you have the more degrees
of freedom you have okay which is not
the case for dimensionality of your
coordinates and that's because you're
looking at commonalities of those
degrees of freedom in in dimensioning
your space
the more Dimensions you have the more
ways the thing can move so there it
turns out in electronics design you can
have multiple clocks so there are sort
of
multiple times within the design and
essentially what singles out a a
particular uh signal as a clock signal
is that it synchronizes a lot of other
signals or it ties things together
connect to a lot of things so which
means there really was only one
time and there a lot of
clocks a lot of clocks is not the same
as a lot of
times what physics would be like if you
the question is if you have regions in
which they are effectively independent
of one another then they would
be so the thing you make a theory with
two times I don't know how when we say
two times we mean at every point of
space there are two times not a region
way out there where is one time in a
region out there where there's another
time I mean every point of space well I
mean I think the amazing thing about our
universe is that is that the geometry
SpaceTime geometry everywhere seems to
be the same yes and it has only one time
you might not it also only has the same
same whatever let him give the lecture
okay it's all right I think that there
are people that don't think it's
nonsense and that's why yeah there are
there
are people who don't think it's
nonsense however it is never um has
never become any part of mainstream uh
thinking and more than one time more
than one time Direction not more than
one clock okay let's let's go
on
um yeah so we have these six extra
dimensions of space how do we get rid of
them and of course you know you know the
answer you roll them up the simplest
model would be a world in which on the
large scale there was one dimension of
space time is there but let's just
freeze time one dimension of space
that's a long line we can imagine
particles on this
line particles move up and down the line
maybe they bind together maybe they form
molecules maybe they do interesting
things uh who knows maybe even they can
form life they can signal each other by
launching a particle from one group to
another group and you can have some
possibly interesting physics these
people who live on this line who are
made up out of these Point particles
well I always like to say they have a
rather boring life each one has a friend
to the left and maybe a friend to the
right but my joke is that they don't
don't have a Social Circle because you
can't have a circle in one dimension
hahaa very very boring life and also
they can't you know they can't pass
through each other they get they they
Bang into each other very boring but
then they look through a high power
microscope and they discover their line
is really surface of a
cylinder now they're too big to feel the
cylinder
they're great big things which move up
and down but that doesn't mean that
there aren't smaller
things and the smaller things now can
move both along the line and
perpendicular to the line so there are
new degrees of freedom there are new
distinctions between particles particles
can move this way they can move this way
they can even move this way and there's
a whole new game
this is the most Elementary and simple
example of
compactification another way you could
think about
it
is let's try to think about higher
Dimensions let's suppose ordinary space
was
two-dimensional but that when the
creatures who lived in this ordinary
space magnified it they discovered a
tiny Third Dimension what might that
look like
okay and uh a third dimension in the
same sense that uh that the circle here
provided a third dimension so here's
here's what it might look
like there's the world that they think
they live
on but now they look under a microscope
and they discover that there's a
direction
perpendicular so there's some thickness
there okay
there's some thickness there we'll call
the top thing the
ceiling and the bottom thing the
floor and there's
some bulk stuff namely space in
between okay now we're going to do
something else having edges like this
makes trouble for Strings the strings
start to fluctuate and eventually they
fluctuate out and get bigger than the uh
uh than the um than the distance between
between the floor and the St the ceiling
but we're going to do something the same
thing we do when
we well what we're going to do is
identify the floor with the
ceiling we could have done this let's go
back to the cylinder the cylinder is
really a
ribbon in which you identify the floor
with the ceiling you say that if you go
out here you come back
here in other words
here's the
ribbon And the cylinder was obtained
from the ribbon by
identifying one edge with the other
Edge when you go out here you come back
in here same thing here the floor and
the ceiling are identified so that when
you go out the ceiling here you reappear
on the
floor now this direction there is no
Edge there's no Edge anymore and this
perpendicular Direction here has the
topology of a circle it's periodically
identified this would be an example of
compactifying one out of three
dimensions can you compactify two out of
three dimensions how many big Dimensions
big ones would be left over if you
compactified two out of
three one so we'd be back to the world
of one dimension but with something new
two two compact Dimensions instead of
one let me show you what that would look
like a particular way of doing
it this is a particular way of doing
it take
a well let me make it
bigger this is kind of a
prism an infinitely long prism would you
call this a prism
that's not prism I guess no prism is a
wrong word
um
uh rectangular something
rather a rectangular what rectangular
parallelopiped except that it's infinite
in an extent okay right now it has edges
but what we're going to do with the
edges is we're going to
identify this edge with this Edge and
this edge with this Edge not just the
edges a point over here
here is identified with a point on the
floor a point on the ceiling is
identified with a point on the floor a
point on the back wall is identified
with a point on the front wall here's
the back wall here's the front wall so
anything that goes out through an edge
reappears on the opposite face at the
same spot that now has compactified and
there's no edges left once you make
these identifications they really are no
edges
anymore uh you to draw it you know to
draw it on a
plane really on a
plane you take the
cylinder you slid it and you open it up
okay so now it looks like it has a floor
and a ceiling but then keep in mind that
the real geometry is identified and has
no Edge same here there are no edges
anybody who walks out one side reappears
at the other and doesn't even notice
it so this is compactifying two out of
three
dimensions how about two out of 10 or
six out of 10 yeah you can do the same
thing
and exactly the same
thing and this process is called
toroidal
compactification okay what does it have
to do with a
Taurus let's talk about Tori because
Tori are the
simplest geometries to use for
compactification the edge of this here
this face over here is a Taurus it
doesn't look like a Taurus doesn't look
like a donut but topologically it's a
donut it's a so let's talk about
Tori the simplest Taurus is a circle
that's a a one-dimensional
Taurus it's just a
circle right you say a circle doesn't
look like a Taurus well it don't worry
about it we're going to define the thing
that does look like a Taurus all right
let's take a
Taurus incidentally when we talk about a
Taurus we're not talking about a shape
embedded in threedimensional
two-dimensional shape bettered in three
dimensions what we're talking about is a
topology we're talking about the
topology of the
boundary not the interior of the Taurus
we're not talking about a solid Taurus
we're not talking about a donut with a
dough on the inside we're talking about
the mathematical surface of the
Taurus okay and what we're talking about
when we see the word Taurus is the
topology of the
surface okay there's a
Taurus and let me now do something to it
I'm going to cut
it over here well let's cut it over here
I'm going to take a scissor and slice it
around here now remember we're not
talking about the stuff that's inside
the Taurus we're only talking about the
surface cut it and open it up what does
it look
like it looks like a finite piece of a
cylinder
right but I have to with uh yeah we
taking it opened up all right it's not
the same as the Taurus but it's
topologically the same as the Taurus as
long as we remember that this point is
identified with this point this point is
identified with this point anybody who
walks along here and Crosses this Edge
that's over here comes back over here
that's over here all right so we've done
the same game except we've taken a
cylinder now and ident
identified the left cut here with the
right cut through the cylinder over here
that is now mathematically a Taurus but
we can go another step we can now take
our scissor and cut it along
Here and Now open it
up and it becomes a
rectangle so a Taurus is topologically
the same as a rectangle but they have to
remember that the rectangle has
identifications if this point is called
a then this is also a if this point is
called B then this is also called B
let's follow the trajectory of a
particle as it moves on a
Taurus a hypothetical particle a fake
particle moving on on a mathematical
Taurus like this what happens to it
let's see if we can follow it let's
suppose it starts over here moving this
way and assume that it moves in a
straight line okay no forces on it what
happens when it gets to
here reappears at the bottom right now
it goes at the same angle because it
hasn't been accelerated and it gets to
over here gets to over here reappears
over here now what goes to here where
does it
reappear back over here
right
okay depending on the angle and
depending on the ratio of the sides of
the Taurus it will either if the ratios
of the sides of the Taurus are rational
and some other good things uh it will
simply repeat itself and eventually find
itself on the original line again uh uh
so that there will be a finite number of
bands like
this and then repeat itself if the
ratios of the sides are incommensurate
or if you some incommensurate
angle then it will just keep going and
going and going essentially filling up
the entire or getting arbitrarily close
to any point on the Taurus but this is
not the important thing the important
thing is that a Taurus is a way of
compactifying space that's exactly what
we did over here we took this and
identified it with this this and
identified it with this so this would be
called a two a compactification of two
Dimensions keeping the third one uncomp
ified but the compactification would be
a Taurus Tori are especially simple uh
geometries for
compactification uh
there are other geometries that you
could try and and people do I can't draw
it quite the same way but you could take
a
line times a
sphere a line times a two dimensional
sphere so that every point on the line a
little fly moving up and down that uh
that or a little insect moving up and
down that line would be able to move
along the line or along a sphere
attached to each point on there just as
just as there's a Taurus attached to
each point here you could do a
sphere uh for reasons that I'll come to
spheres are not good things to compact a
f on all right so this is the toroidal
now can you do the same thing with um
higher Dimensions let's suppose we
had supposing we wanted to get rid of
three dimensions to get rid of three
dimensions we want to invent a thing
called a three Taurus a
three-dimensional Taurus we want to take
three of the dimensions and make them
into a tus yes that's not hard you do
exactly the same thing you take a
cube doesn't have to be a
cube a
uh parallelopiped or whatever you call
it and now do the same kind of
identifications this face over here a is
identified with this face face over here
a this one over here B with this one b
and the back side of
a a c this is on the back is identified
with C in the
front that becomes what is called the
three Taurus it has the topology of a
three Taurus again no edges although if
you try to draw it you draw it with
edges and that would effectively shrink
three directions if you made the Torah
small in any case if you made it
physically small it would hide three
dimensions at least from your Co grain
uh measurements so if you're doing
String Theory in 10 dimensions and you
compactify three 10 SpaceTime dimensions
compactify three you would
have
uh seven dimensions left over one time
in six space that's also not what we
want so what do we want to
do we want to make a we want to get rid
of Six
Dimensions so we make a six
Taurus a six Taurus I can't draw on the
Blackboard for
you I suppose I could draw a for Taurus
but uh we get we clutter up the
Blackboard terribly what's what's the
figure that the four Cube called when
you what yeah yeah yeah yeah and then
identify faces of that but um or volumes
of it you'd be identifying volumes of it
but um
mathematically all you're doing is
adding axes and keeping and making
identifications a it seems like all
these Dimensions all these spatial
Dimensions greater than three uh come
back on themselves uh yeah is there some
they're periodically
identified what they're periodically
identified yeah they come back on
themselves is that that's fundamental
like I guess well can't go infinite like
X Y and Z can you could have six or 10
or nine whatever it is Dimensions which
don't come back on themselves it just
wouldn't be our
world you ask why did nature choose to
uh to compactify some dimensions and not
others that we haven't got the vaguest
idea but uh we do know that we live in a
world of three dimensions why do we
assume the other dimensions are
spatial String Theory or or no other
theory that I know Quantum field theory
none of them makes sense with more than
one time
Dimension yeah we know we have one real
time Dimension but there's no more room
for for more but why beyond the the four
do we assume that the remaining
dimensions are spatial else could they
be what else would they be what else
should they be I'm I'm not well I've got
some ideas but my my my point is that
just because we can't identify what they
are why do we assume that they are
spatial and curled up as opposed to
something that elsea we just don't
understand because we can understand
this it doesn't mean it's the real world
it means it's a thing we can
study find out its properties see how it
behaves and compare it with the real
world if you just say maybe it's
something and we don't know what it is
okay that we'll stop
Dead
uh this is
easy it's
straightforward it's not enormously
subtle not not these torai These torai
are pretty easy they're not enormously
subtle they're solvable we can work out
what particle physics is like we can
work out uh what the what the world on
in such a uh setup is like and we can
ask how close is it how similar is it to
the real world that's the only reason
it's a uh it's a setup that we know and
understand it has gravity it has quantum
mechanics it has particles it has bosons
it has firion and we can study
it it also has black holes so we can
study the black holes and find out if
they do this or that that's that's the
reason what does it
lack it's too
symmetric it has super Symmetry and
other symmetries that are just too
symmetric right some things it lacks and
some things it has too much
of yeah yeah um when you take the bagel
and turn it into a rectangle um
topologically are equivalent but if you
look at the distance fly on the inside
of it yeah don't think about the
distances
right this is these are when when a
mathematician speaks about a
Taurus or a physicist for the most part
he's talking about a
topology not talking about a
geometry now in
fact the Taurus when it's presented as
a rectangle oh let's let's talk a little
bit about how many uh how many
inequivalent Tori there are
what is the what are the parameters of a
Taurus all right it's a
rectangle so first of all it has an
overall
area okay or equivalently it has a
length and a height a width and a height
okay so it has a width and a
height which are two
parameters one of those parameters is
the size of it you could take it to be
the area
call that a size parameter the other is
the and that's the product of the length
times the uh the width times the height
there's also the ratio of the width
times the height you could call it the
what aspect ratio or the
shape all right so here is a long thin
Taurus here is a broad fat
Taurus but these are the same
these are really the same Taurus oh that
is to say they're geometrically
identical they're geometrically
identical every point on here is
equivalent to a point on here this maps
to this this maps to this we've just
turned the picture on its side and we
haven't made a
new kind of Taurus all right so one
thing we can say is there's the ratio of
the sides
but the ratio of the sides does not go
from
uh zero to
Infinity it goes from one to
Infinity why one to Infinity because
when it's less than one the ratio let's
say of the horizontal to the
vertical this is bigger than one this is
less than one but they're the same
Taurus so the ratio of the sides can
vary from uh from basically from one to
Infinity Z to well from zero to one
either way either way you in fact
usually take from zero to one and go
from zero to one anything else is there
anything else that uh that you can do to
change the Taurus and the answer is yes
here's the game that we haven't
discussed let's go back to
our p P of
cylinder we're going to identify the
left Edge the left Circle over here with
the right Circle over here but before we
do it let's imagine a Twist a Twist by
an angle so that you don't identify this
point with this one up here but you
identify it with a displaced angular
point this one over here is identified
with here this one over here here
identified with that you imagine in your
mind before making the
identification making a little
twist right and then making the
identification that's something new and
what it looks like let's
say let's let's do it vertically let's
draw it this
way make a little twist here before we
make the
identification so that slides things
along the top Edge if we didn't do the
twist we would have a
rectangle if we do the twist then we
don't identify this point with this one
we identify it with that
point this point with that point and we
might as well draw
it like
this we might as well draw it as well
that doesn't look very neat that's not
quite
right
yeah all right everything in the bottom
gets identified with a point uh above
it and everything on the left gets
identified but with this offset with
this angle so to parameterize
Tori there's the aspect ratio there's
the there's the
size that can be taken to be the overall
area then
getting rid of the area and let's say
unit things of unit area there's the
aspect ratio and there's the
angle these things are called moduli
These are the moduli of the Taurus there
are three of them the three moduli of
the Taurus so the overall size the ratio
of the height to the width and the angle
the lean the angle of
Leaning these have technical
names a Twist is called a Dane twist DN
after a mathematician I suppose named
Dane
uh the overall volume is called a Kor
modulus and
the
ratio aspect aspect ratio is called a
complex structure moduli and they have
technical
meanings uh if you see them you'll know
roughly what they
mean could you flip it as well seems
like flip the
ring as well flip it you mean reflect it
yeah then you make a then you make a
climb bottle it's is a different
topology you mean if you uh if you take
if you take this point over
here identify it with a point in the
front this point with that point this
point with that point and this one with
the one in the
back that's a Klein
bottle that's not a that's not a that's
it's not a um a
Taurus it's not it's not an orientable
manifold what about nonuniform
twist it has to be a map but an
arbitrary continuous yeah
yeah you can that's right that's right
you can absorb that kind of thing into
the metric on the
Taurus you're right there are other ways
of deforming the Taurus
but those can be absorbed into the
metric on the
Taurus
um these Tori are all flat they have
flat geometries or they can be given
flat geometries they since they can be
drawn on the Blackboard without
stretching them I don't mean the real I
don't mean the real donut the real donut
is a truly curved surface
it has
curvature on the outer boundary it has
positive curvature on the inner near the
hole here it has negative
curvature I'm talking about this um this
mathematical structure that's been
mapped onto the plane in this way it's
completely flat triangles on it have
180° uh some of their angles even on
this
one and particular it's not only flat
but it's reachy flat it's reachy flat
and it's
flat and so string theory on these
geometries is well defined it's a good
uh good mathematical structure for
string theory to exist on it's by far
the easiest way to hide uh other
dimensions and it's called toroidal
compactification it's not good for it's
not good for the real world the real
world is more complex than that
um but I thought I would show you what
the simplest form of compactification is
now I'm going to let's see let's take a
5 minute break somebody wanted to make
an announcement I can't remember yeah
there there you
are yeah Tori are all
flat Tori are all flat
Tori is the plural of Taurus you realize
Tori are all flat in any number of
dimensions
uh and therefore they're also richy flat
and because they're richy
flat String Theory strings moving on
Tori are good things they have a
sensible well- defined
mathematics there are other richy flat
spaces uh where you can take six
dimensions that you don't like and get
rid of them by compactifying them not on
a Taurus or Not by replacing them by
aurus but by replacing them by other
richy flat
manifolds
um in particular there are a class of
Richi flat manifolds which are known as
cabal
manifolds which have very special
properties and where string theory is a
good theory these are incredibly
complicated they're far beyond the uh
the scope of this
course but they're also
the kind of things that string theorists
uh which have enough
complexity and lack of symmetry that
they do look more like the real
world uh but they don't really involve
any really new Concepts that we some
mathematical Concepts to be sure they're
very mathematically difficult objects
but no really new principles uh uh come
out of uh they just look more like the
real world and I'm not going to try to
get into
them uh Taurus is good enough for us we
can see some very interesting things
when we start to explore string theory
on a
Taurus okay let's uh let's go
let's take as a model for Simplicity
just the infinite one-dimensional World
with an extra Dimension that goes around
in a
loop you see why I call a circle a
onedimensional
Taurus it's just a line
element uh periodically identified all
right let's start with that all right we
can have a particle which moves around
on
here and it can have a component of
motion horizontally
nothing special about that that's just
the uh that's just the momentum along
the direction it would have been there
even if you hadn't compa well even if
you didn't have the extra Dimension
you'd have momentum along that direction
but you also have momentum along the
other direction you can have both of
them at the same time a particle moving
sort of
obliquely so of spiraling around this
thing would have a component of momentum
horizontally and a component of momentum
along the circle the components of
momentum along along the circle are
quantized
momenta
uh momenta on periodic spaces are always
quantized the easiest way to see it is
just to say supposing um supposing the
the circumference of this
circle let's just call a circumference 2
pi
r that's just that's just what I'm
calling the
circumference if I take the momentum
along the r Direction there the momentum
along sorry along the circumference
let's call that P along the
circumference PC P along the
circumference and I multiply it by R
which is the circumference divided by 2
pi I get something which looks like an
angular momentum in fact it is a kind of
angular momentum it's there's an angle
associated with this uh Circle just an
angular position along here and P * R
that's just like it is like angular
momentum okay that's quantized in
integer
multiples of Plank's
constant
so the momentum
along the circumference the momenta
along the
circumference is quantized in units if
we set plunk constant to
one then the unit of momentum is 1 /
R let's suppose the particle we're
talking about is
massless if it happens to be a massless
particle then its momentum or the
magnitude of its momentum is the same as
the magnitude of its
energy energy for a massless particle is
equal to the momentum of course there a
factor of the speed of light apart from
the factor of the speed of light energy
is equal to the magnitude of the
momentum this component of the momentum
can be positive or negative and it's an
integer the implication is that there's
a that there is a quantized amount of
energy even if the particle is not
moving along the horizontal direction if
it's moving in the circular D Direction
it has an energy which is n units
divided by
R all right that energy it's from our
point of view why we don't see the
circular Direction it's just a thing
standing still it's a thing standing
still but the manifestation of the fact
that it's moving is that it has some
energy it has some mass mass mass this
is the mass now of the particle and it
comes in integer
multiples of 1 / R the smaller R is the
bigger the
spacing between mass
levels okay the bigger the spacing
between mass levels so by knowing the
spacing of course we we don't measure
any of this but uh principle by
measuring the spacing between the masses
of these different particles how are
they different they're different from a
macroscopic from our point of view they
look different they have different
masses from the point of view of a small
object you know a small detector which
can see inside this thing they're just
particles which have different
components of momentum in this
direction um we we'll call them
different particles because they have
different different masses and the
spectrum of them namely the spacing
between them tells us how big the
internal space
is the bigger the internal space the
closer the levels let's draw a level
diagram energy energy equals z or
mass mass equals z is right over here
then we can have + one
unit of rotational momentum around here
that would give us a particle of mass 1
/
R and so forth what about if n is
negative does that mean it has negative
energy no the uh the energy is the
absolute value I think I erased it the
energy is always positive so there's a
particle of mass 1/ R here there's a
particle of mass 1 R here 2 over
R minus or 2 over R the spacing between
the mass levels is a direct reflection
of how big the circle is the smaller the
circle the larger the
spacing if this circle is very very
big then the levels are very very close
together so if we discovered excited
states of particles which were very very
very very densely
spaced we would say o it looks like
there's an extra big rather big
Dimension if we find that the spacing
due to this kind of motion is very very
sparse then we say that Dimension is
small right
okay so these are the energy levels
for the components of mass of a the mass
of a particle where the particle is
simply a particle moving around this
direction now you can do something else
in a compact space you can have a
different kind of particle which from
the outside meaning from the big
Dimensions just looks like a particle
but which has an entirely different
structure oh
incidentally if all particles are
strings if particles really are strings
then I might want to draw this as a
little string over here
but just think of it as an almost tiny
little particle let's forget the fact
that it spreads out it's a tiny particle
and it moves around the whole Center of
mass of it moves around and gives it a a
series of energies in this way but
there's something else you can do the
other thing you can do with a
string and a compact space like this is
wind the string around like that
here this band around here is once wound
around the cylinder of the cup I could
take a rubber band and wind it around
that
way that can also move up and down the
axis it's first of all it's localized
it's at a definite place in the big
Dimensions so it has a location from our
point of view it can move it can move up
and down it's a particle
it's also a particle it's a particle
which is wound around the extra
Dimension what is its mass what is its
mass its mass now is not due to its
motion in this direction it's due to the
potential energy of stretching a string
around that uh
distance how much energy would you
expect there to be in a string stretched
around here the answer is clearly going
to be proportional to the length of the
string there's a certain tension and
energy per unit length for every string
let's set it equal to one we won't worry
about units tonight tonight I'll ignore
units set set just work in units where
the string tension is one if a string is
stretched out to a certain distance then
the mass that that string has is
proportional to the length of the
stretch
string how about a string which is
wrapped around this direction what do
expect its uh its mass to be
proportional
to the circumference R yeah the radius
of circumference
so this one will have a mass equal to r
or proportional to R but you know you
can wrap it around several
times that I can't do with the uh with a
coffee cup but I can draw it I think
no no but I want to connect it back
together again uh oh I know I know I got
it yeah
um it it crosses here and connects back
here can you see it if I had a rubber
band I could wrap it you can wrap a
rubber band twice around here you take
it twist it and put it on here all right
how about this one what's the what's the
mass of it how much energy does it have
2 R twice as much twice as much
stretching so we
have R we have energy R we have energy 2
R 3 R 4 R if the string has an
orientation in other words if you think
of the string as having a direction then
you can wrap it positively or you can
wrap it negatively here's one wrapped
positively here's one wrapped negatively
so this wrapping or winding number it's
called winding number the winding number
can be positive imagine you have a
rubber band and on the rubber band you
draw little arrows to give it a sense of
direction and you're going to wrap it
around your wrist you can wrap it around
your wrist so the arrows run this way or
so that they run this
way so the winding number can be either
positive or negative but whatever the
winding number is the mass of that
string is equal to the absolute is R
times the absolute value of the winding
number okay so there's another spectrum
of particles
here and that spectrum of particles has
energy levels whose distance is not
proportional to 1 / R but it's
proportional to R itself let's suppose R
is very small let's suppose that R is
very very
small then this spacing is
large and this spacing is very
small it takes very little energy to
wrap around a small
circle okay but for the particles which
are not wrapped but which are or not
wound around but which are moving around
literally moving and have momentum the
spacing between levels is large if R is
small so we have these two Spectra of
two different kinds of
particles one is
called These are these ones here are
called cutline particles they were this
idea has been around uh of particles
having momentum in an extra compact
direction that goes back to beginnings
of general
relativity uh kuta first had the idea
1917 I think and it's grown up a great
deal since then
but String
Theory introduced the new idea of wound
particles particles wound around and
they have very complimentary kind of
Spectra so if you see particles with a
large spacing you must also see
particles with a small
spacing both combinations together would
tell you something about the uh the
nature of the compact
directions but no noce that there's no
way to make the spacing arbitrarily
large here without having very small
spacing here small spacing of course
means that it just takes a little bit of
energy to create one of these things on
the other hand what happens if you take
R very big now imagine taking R very big
if you take R very big then the spacing
of these kutac Cline particles is very
small these are very close to together
now R is very big 1 / R is very small
these become very closely spaced and
what happens to
these they get very widely spaced why
because it just takes a lot of energy to
wrap it around a very very big cylinder
here so you have these two complementary
kinds of particles there's almost a
symmetry there's almost a symmetry of
the spectrum where you replace R by 1 /
R you replace R by 1 / R and you replace
momentum by winding
number and what happens you just
interchange these two and the Spectrum
stays the
same that seems to be a symmetry of the
spectrum of of uh of string
theory this only applies to the extra
Dimensions there's no way to wrap a
string around the X the real x axis it's
infinite but as applied to the x
Dimensions there seems to be a symmetry
where you replace R by 1 /
R winding by momentum around that
direction and the system comes back to
itself that vertical versus the
horizontal no no no no this is not the
vertical versus the horizontal this is
The Duality between winding number
and and momentum and kusine momentum now
from what I've told you it's hardly
clear that this is an
exact um equivalence in every possible
respect it's just an equivalence of the
energy spectrum of some uh some simple
particles in fact it's an exact symmetry
of the theory if you take a compact
direction and you start shrinking it
down smaller and smaller well at some
point
incidentally the uh the Spectra will be
equal there some some radius there's
some radius where the spacing between
the Kut aine particles and the winding
particles will be the same we could call
that R equals 1 in some units at r equal
1 the Spectrum are the same otherwise
they cross
um if you try if you start trying to
make the radius of compactification
smaller and smaller you eventually get
to this point where when you cross it
you can either think of it as saying
that the size is smaller than one or you
can interchange winding and momentum and
say it's bigger than
one there's no
sense in in a certain sense uh there
it's not possible to think about String
Theory where R is smaller than a certain
size oh you can think of it if you want
to make it smaller than a certain size
but all that happens is it rearranges
itself so that it looks like string
theory on the larger
space yeah uh does r less than one and R
greater than one are those different
kinds of particles are they all fans or
oh every Fons bons they all they all do
the same thing oh so there's 10 or 26
Dimensions it's uh implies to both yeah
yeah it implies to every compact
Direction here I've only indicated one
compact
Direction Circle we can apply it to
problems with several compact directions
but this is a kind of freakish
surprising result that's characteristic
really of string theory it is not
characteristic of uh Point particles
moving in U unclosed spaces like this
it's The Interchange of winding with
momentum that hardly seems an obvious
thing to do remarkably the entire Theory
the scattering amplitudes the spectrum
of particles the whole
works uh is symmetric under this
interchange One open strings and the
other closed strings no no no no they're
both closed strings closed strings
closed strings open strings it doesn't
make any sense to wind around they just
unwind themselves no no they're both
closed
strings in a theory I I should have said
that in a theory of closed strings
there's this interchange symmetry
right open strings are a little more
complicated yeah and we'll talk about
them that be similar to the black hole
analogy where Dimensions become Tim like
and time becomes Dimension like nope
nope nope what it is is it's saying that
there's a certain distance where when
you try to think of string theory on a
space smaller than that it's equivalent
to string theory on a space bigger than
that
trying to shrink the diameter of a
compactification to arbitrarily small
distances you get frustrated it just
rearranges itself so that it looks like
the theory on a bigger space space does
that help get rid of self
energies well it does say in some sense
there's a smallest uh smallest size
scale in string theory but
uh
uh keeps things from being infinite yes
um that's well that's true if you have a
winding number right I me what's what's
to say that there is a winding number is
that just a theoretical model or is
there an analogy to physical
space
um so in the absence of a winding number
right and you have just if you have a
compact
Dimension then it's possible to think of
strings which are well are you asking
maybe you're asking how you make them if
you don't have them to begin with yeah
well I'm asking if if there is no
existence of a winding number a winding
number or a particle with a winding
number particle with a winding number
you can make
them I'll show you how to make
them we do have to start with something
so we start with a particle which has no
winding number that's a little string
that looks like
that okay now we take this and we pull
it around we stretch it out it's still
got no winding
number it's not wound around the thing
and now we stretch it all the ways
around here so it comes back the back
side and comes up over
here can you see what I've done it still
has no winding
number the winding number of this piece
is canceled out by the winding number of
that piece so you take your arm you take
the rubber band and you pull it around
and then take uh you know and take the
two pieces here and that's what you're
left with that still has no winding
number but remember now that in string
theory the basic process of
interaction is for things like this to
become things like this we
rearrangement so if you sit there for a
while this string will rearrange and
form that now what does this have it has
two particles with opposite winding
number okay we still have nit zero
winding number one is wound one way one
is wound the other way but now they're
disconnected and they're free to
separate throw that one away just eject
it out of the system give it some uh
velocity and when it gets off to Alpha
centur forget about it and you're left
with a with a particle with winding
number
uh so whether whether you like them or
not you can't forbid
them some things you can try to forbid
you can say if they're not there to
begin with they'll never be
there uh possibly some things you can't
forbid because you can imagine that the
process of the theory itself the
important processes in the theory can
force them on you and these get forced
on you of course they always get forced
in
pairs but you
can that's that's uh you throw away half
of them and just uh do some experiments
with the remaining
ones and this is with increasing energy
I guess then the uh the Kusa
Cline closed string gets larger that
would be more energy yeah it does it
gets some energy from not only from the
momentum but from being stretched yeah
it takes energy to do
it
uh but you know this is the sort of
thing which would happen if you collided
two
particles with no winding number just
two cut aine particles you Collide them
hard every possible combination of stuff
happens and among the things which would
happen is these winding and anti-winding
things we go flying
off uh it's and the logic is the same as
the logic of electric charge supposing
the world started with no electric
charge does that mean there would be no
electrons no any kind of collision that
would take place uh would create
electrons and positrons and then the
positrons could go flying off to some
other place and you'd be left with
electrons so the logic is really no
different than electric charge you can't
not have electric charge because you can
always make it in
pairs uh
the net charge in the world might be
zero for all we
know um the net winding number might be
zero but who cares we can do experiments
on uh on you
know on a region which contains a uh a
winding number so yeah so this has a
name
incidentally the equivalence between
theories which look different
usually called a
duality this is called T
Duality capital T Duality and the T in
this case stands for
Taurus T stands for Taurus this is
Taurus Duality or t
Duality and as I say it's a duality
which relates compactifications on very
small geometries to compactifications on
big geometries and it's a rather
startling thing thing I mean it uh when
it was first discovered it surprised
everybody what it means is that geometry
defined in terms of how
strings
the geometry can also often be recovered
or partly recovered from the spectrum of
modes uh on a uh the geometry of a drum
head the shape of a drum head there's a
famous mathematical question can the
shape of a drum head be predicted from
the sound that it makes from the uh from
the spectrum of vibrations the answer is
not quite but you can predict a lot of
the shape of the drum head the same
question applies to these
compactifications from the spectrum of
particles the spectrum of vibrational
energies vibrational and other kinds of
energies can you predict the shape and
or the size of the compact directions
and the answer is yes to a largic
extent um
but there are some
ambiguities and some
dualities that you can't tell if it's a
tiny geometry or if it's a big geometry
because these two go into each
other that would not be the case with a
drum I assure
you uh you would not mistake a small
drum for a big drum yeah okay
good for more please visit us at
stanford.edu